Hello, my name is Stefan Balslev and I'm
going to talk to you about a challenge
that many developers face every day.
The challenge of changing out a lower
dependency.
To change out a dependency,
you need to remove all the things that
depend on it first.
And like this game here, there is some
rules to it. You have to remove them in
a certain order and there's certain
order in which things have to come back.
Managing these kind of dependencies can
be very hard. Let's look at an example.
So here, I want to remove an app and
change it out with a new version. The
core version in the bottom version one,
I want to change with the new version, a
new version of that extension. So what
do I need to do? Well, first I need to
remove all the extensions that depend on
it.
I'll do that one by one. So uninstall,
unpublish, and all of that work. And
then, of course, I'll remove the
extension itself and replace it with a
new one. Again here, I'll do the
publish, the sync, the install. I'll
then start to install all the other
extensions that were on top. One, two,
three, and then so on. Seems fairly
simple. It's full life cycle operations
with the uninstall, unpublish, publish,
sync, install, and then install all of
the rest of the applications.
Seems very simple, right? VS Code does
that for you when you press F5. It
detects the changes that you've made in
your project and tries to do all of this
for you.
But what happens when this go wrong?
Let's look at that.
What happens if one of them doesn't
compile?
Again, we apply the core version two and
then we see there's one that applied and
reinstalled and went well. We tried
another one and it didn't go so well.
So what happened here? Well, it couldn't
compile. We did some changes in the core
app that are no longer compatible with
the extension that we're trying to
install on top.
So now the process halts. And in this
case, yes, it halts and I'm broken. I
can't do anything. If I'm in VS code and
I press F5 and I end up in this
situation,
it can be quite hard sometimes to get
back to the original state on the left
side here
in order for me to continue and retry
the development. And this is the part
that we've been working hard to get
right.
So let's look at it.
So in my service here, I have these apps
installed. Let's see it.
Extension management.
So here I have the four apps we talked
about before. There's the core, there's
the customer agent, invoice agent, and
enhancements on top of invoices.
So same scenario, same setup, seems
fairly simple. I'll open VS code
and find a project that I've been
working on.
So as many of us, when we are working
with projects, we do not have everything
loaded in a workspace. We have the
projects that we are working on, they
are loaded in this workspace.
In this case, I'm working on the
customer agent and the core, so I am
uh in a project in a workspace where
these two are present. The other ones
may be also my projects, but they may
not be in this workspace or they might
be third-party products that depend on
my core.
Nevertheless, I am looking at this and
now I'm going to do a change.
So I'm going to go here.
I'm going to change this to a secret
text.
This is a good change because we want to
make sure that our tokens cannot be
debugged. So we make sure that it's a
secret text that we return. I could add
non-debuggable and so forth, but now
let's just stop here and say we did a
small change of this return type.
This is a breaking change and we'll see
it immediately in this workspace because
there is a dependency down here that
lights up red and says that well, it's
not a text anymore. It is a secret text.
Fair enough. Now I've changed that into
a secret text also. We are happy,
everything is green. I press F5
and we start compiling and we start
publishing and we'll see what happens
when we publish this to my local service
here. Let's see. Give it a second here.
It will do the whole lifecycle
operations for everything on top and
then you'll try to reapply the new
versions
and it says here
something did not work. Something did
not work and it was all in vain here. So
publishing failed. So something is
depending on the the fact that I changed
this from a text to a secret text and we
can see that here.
The new thing we'll see now is this part
here. The original extensions have been
restored.
So why is this?
Why is this even possible? Well,
we have a option in the launch config
called dependency publishing options.
Let's go look at it.
So with this one set
I can instruct
the deployment of these apps to
recompile all direct dependencies of the
changed app. So setting it to default
here will recompile all the direct
dependencies of the changed app whether
or not they're in the workspace I'm
working on.
So in this case I changed both the core
and the customer agent extensions.
When they were published all the
extensions that were installed on the
system that depended on the on them were
recompiled as they were installed again.
Of course, the invoicing agent failed
because it was depending on this one
causing the whole thing to fail.
And because we have improved the way we
detect what is getting published and
uninstalled and ready to be reapplied,
we can now restore this.
There are other options in this
dependency publishing option. The ignore
will only recompile the the published
app or the changed app. So, in this
case, if I'm changing the core, then
only the core will be recompiled and
you'll start getting runtime errors
for all the dependencies.
The strict requires that you have all
the dependencies in the workspace. So,
it will fail from the get-go because
there is more dependencies to the core
app than is in this workspace.
I'll need to include the invoicing agent
also in order for this to work.
Okay, there are still some scenarios
where this will break. It's not solving
all the problems. One of the core
scenarios is is that we do not support
in Business Central
uh the downgrade of apps because they
have destructive changes or they could
have destructive changes.
Your install logic of a newer version
may have some logic that changes the
data that is not compatible with the
older version, your schema changes, and
so forth. Lots of things can change and
you with a a version change, you
indicate that something major has
happened, something significant has
happened. So, if you change the version
as part of a small change,
then it does not work with the restore.
However, for a normal developer like me
looking here and changing some small
things, pressing every every F5 every
now and then, this will be a great help
for my productivity because I don't have
to go back and restore manually this
extension setup that I had before.
So, now you know much more about
dependency publishing and you can learn
much more about it from the learn site.
The link is below.
Thank you for watching.